Prateksha Udhayanan

pratekshau@gmail.com | +91-7760689583 | GitHub | LinkedIn | Website

Research Interests

My research interests primarily revolve around computer vision, particularly in the field of controllable synthesis of visual content such as images, videos, and graphic designs. I am especially keen on utilizing multi-modal **constraints** to effectively guide the generation.

EDUCATION

Integrated Masters of Technology in Computer Science (BTech+MTech)

Bangalore, India 2017 - 2022

International Institute of Information Technology, Bangalore; CGPA: 3.76/4.00

Publications and Preprints

- [WACV 2024] KJ Joseph, Prateksha Udhayanan, Tripti Shukla, Aishwarya Agarwal, Srikrishna Karanam, Koustava Goswami, and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Iterative Multi-granular Image Editing using Diffusion Models - Accepted at WACV 2024 LINK
- [WACV 2023] Prateksha Udhayanan, Suryateja BV, Parth Laturia, Dev Chauhan, Darshan Khandelwal, Stefano Petrangeli, and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Recipe 2 Video: Synthesizing Personalized Videos from Recipe Texts. In Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (pp. 2268-2277). 2023 [LINK]
- [SN Computer Science] Chinchu Thomas, Prateksha Udhayanan, Ayush Yadav, and Dinesh Babu Jayagopi. Multimodal Unsupervised Domain Adaptation for Predicting Speaker Characteristics from Video -Accepted at SN Computer Science journal
- [AI-ML Systems 2021] Arjun Verma, Prateksha Udhayanan, Rahul Murali Shankar, Nikhil KN, and Sujit Kumar Chakrabarti. Source-Code Similarity Measurement: Syntax Tree Fingerprinting for Automated Evaluation, The First International Conference on AI-ML-Systems (pp. 1-7). 2021) [LINK]
- [Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications] Prateksha Udhayanan, Swasti S Mishra, and Shrisha Rao. Firm dynamics and employee performance management in duopoly markets Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications. (583, p.126298). 2021 [LINK]
- Koustava Goswami, Srikrishna Karanam, Joseph K J, Prateksha Udhayanan and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Contextual Prompt Learning for Vision-Language Understanding - Under review at AAAI 2024 [LINK]
- Prateksha Udhayanan, Srikrishna Karanam, and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Learning with Multi-modal Gradient Attention for Explainable Composed Image Retrieval - [arXiv:2308.16649]

Patents

- Prateksha Udhayanan, Srikrishna Karanam, and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Text-Conditioned Visual Attention for Multimodal Machine Learning Models (US Patent App. 18/351,211)
- Prateksha Udhayanan, Dev Chauhan, Parth Laturia, Darshan Khandelwal, Suryateja BV, Stefano Petrangeli, and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Auto-Generating Video to Illustrate a Procedural Document (US Patent App. 17/661,614)
- Koustava Goswami, Srikrishna Karanam, Joseph KJ, Prateksha Udhayanan, and Balaji Vasan Srinivasan. Generating Text Prompts for Digital Images Utilizing Vision-Language Models and Contextual Prompt Learning (US Patent App. 18/342,954)

Experience

Adobe Research, Bangalore, India

Research Associate July 2022 - Present

- o Part of the Collaborative Creativity team, working on a range of projects focused on computer vision, and multi-modal content understanding. Submitted papers, filed patents and developed research technologies that were successfully integrated into products.
- Key project themes: image retrieval techniques with multimodal inputs, image editing techniques, automated creation and editing of graphic designs, layout and color optimizations for graphic designs.

Slice, India - a fintech startup

Mentors: Saksham Agarwal, Khushal Bokadey

Software Engineering Intern

- January 2022 June 2022 o Contributed to designing and building a Microservice for **credit-based non-card transactions** in a three-member team.
- Implemented code in Spring Boot for Paytm and bank transfers; optimized the algorithm for computing transfer charges.
- o Developed High-Level Design (HLD) and Low-Level Design (LLD) considering database requirements and schema design.
- Setup infrastructure pipelines, automated build, test, and deployment workflows across different environments.
- o Internal Reconciliation Service Led the development of an internal reconciliation service, designed to compare records maintained by Slice with transaction details provided by external entities.

Adobe Research, Bangalore, India

Research Intern [Published in WACV 2023]

May 2021 - August 2021

Mentor: Balaji Vasan Srinivasan

- o Built a novel end-to-end deep-learning based architecture to convert instructional documents into multimodal videos.
- Implemented novel re-ranking schemes for retrieving and selecting the optimal combination of multimodal visuals consistent with user constraints.
- Used Viterbi-algorithm-based optimization for multi-modal frame selection, resulting in a coherent video composition.
- o Established evaluation metrics based on cognitive models of procedural text understanding.

Anveshan

Software Engineering Intern at Anveshan

Mentor: Ayush Goyal

March 2020 - April 2020

- Collaborated closely with the startup's tech team to develop an application for operational supply chain management, to help eliminate middlemen from the supply chain and promote fair trade for farmers.
- o Co-led the designing and development of the back-end for an Inventory Management app using Django.
- Implemented Optical Character Recognition techniques to enable automated product quality check verifying MRP and expiry date.

Siemens Technology and Services Pvt. Ltd. Bangalore

Research Intern

Mentor: Varghese Alex

May 2020 - July 2020

- Implemented a LSTM-based hierarchical model in TensorFlow for Anomaly Detection in procedural videos.
- The model is trained to learn the sequential structure of procedural activities from text domain and transfer it to visual domain which enables visual appearance learning and future prediction.

Multimodal Perception Lab (MPL) - IIITB

Research Intern at MPL

Mentor: Dr.Dinesh Babu J June 2019 - September 2019

Mentor: Julia Nguyen, Camille Villa

- Translation system for Indian Sign Language estimated the 3D coordinates of the hand joints using deep 3D CNN models from input depth images.
- $\circ\,$ The predicted coordinates are mapped and rendered on a human avatar.
- Reduced the gesture generation time for each sign from 20 minutes to less than 2 minutes by automating the process.

Rails Girls Summer of Code Scholar'18

ization

July 2018 - Sept 2018

- Software Engineering Intern at "if-me" organization
 - o Improved the UI and built several accessible and modular ReactJS components and wrote tests in Enzyme and Jest.

Selected Projects

Design Co-pilot

Adobe Research | Being integrated to product

- Implemented novel methodologies to generate graphic design variants based on color, layout and content.
- Designed and built an end-to-end pipeline to edit and transform a design based on user prompt.

o Designed and developed a full stack feature for blocking and reporting users using Ruby on Rails.

- $\circ\,$ Implemented transformer-based masked filed prediction approach for layout and color optimization in design.
- $\circ~$ Developed a latent-space iteration technique to enable iterative editing of images in design workflows.

Generating Cinemagraphs by Animating Elements from a Single Image Input

Adobe Research

- o Currently working on a method to animate periodic motions involving large displacements using a single image as input.
- Helped in product integration of automatic animation for fluid elements such as water, smoke, and fire, from a single image.

Composed Image Retrieval

Adobe Research

- Developed a novel multi-modal gradient attention computation mechanism for composed image retrieval.
- Proposed an end-to-end learning scheme for vision-language siamese transformers with our attention-based loss function.
- $\circ~$ Significantly improved the performance by $\approx 4\%$ on Recall@1 metric.

Firm Dynamics and Employee Performance Management in Duopoly Markets

Supervisor - Dr. Shrisha Rao | [Published in Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications 2021]

- o Modeled and studied the effects of different performance management strategies in a firm using agent-based simulations.
- Studied the effects of Peter Principle on firms competing in Stackelberg games and Cournot games.

Syntax Tree Fingerprinting for Automated Evaluation

Supervisor - Dr. Sujit Kumar Chakrabarti | [Published in AI-ML Systems 2021]

- o Developed a winnowing-based AST fingerprinting technique to compute structural similarity between two programs.
- Built a dataset of 7 problems with 100 samples each. Developed evaluation rubrics for these problems to test the system.

Multimodal Unsupervised Domain Adaptation for Predicting Speaker Characteristics from Video

Supervisor - Dr. Dinesh Babu Jayagopi | [Accepted in SN Computer Science journal]

- o Built multimodal unsupervised domain adaptation framework for predicting speaker qualities from videos.
- o Used knowledge distillation along with adversarial discriminative domain adaptationn
- Curated a dataset of videos obtained from informal online learning platform and annotated it with speaker characteristics.

Composite Hybrid Visualization Tool for Unbalanced Bipartite Graphs

Supervisor - Dr. Jaya Sreevalsan Nair | [Project Report]

- o Designed and built a visualization tool in D3.js that integrates matrix representation and radial graph layout.
- o Implemented algorithms for edge-rendering and node-ordering: force-directed edge bundling and Barycentric ordering.

A Java-Based Tool for Storing OWL Ontologies in Object Oriented Databases

Supervisor - Dr. Chandrashekar Ramanathan | [GitHub]

- Implemented various static mapping and dynamic mapping rules to persist OWL ontologies in ObjectDB databases.
- Built an inferencing engine based on forward chaining algorithm for inverse, transitive, and symmetric properties.
- o Integrated a querying tool that converts input queries from SPARQL to JPQL and retrieves results from the OODB.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Winner of CodeHers Coding Challenge 2021: One of the top 15 winners out of 50,000+ women participants.
- Dean's Merit List: Part of the Dean's Merit List 2018, 2020, 2021, 2022 for academic excellence.
- Rails Girls Summer of Code Scholar '18: One of the 7 full-time teams selected out of 200+ international teams.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Graduate Teaching Assistant: AI 511 Machine Learning (September 2021 December 2021)
- Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: ESS 112 Programming in Python (November 2020 March 2021)
- Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: ESS 201 Programming II (C++, Java) (August 2020 December 2020)

MISCELLANEOUS PROJECTS

- Unsupervised Visual Representation Learning: Conducted a detailed study and analysis of unsupervised visual representation learning methods like MoCo, SimCLR and PIRL. Implemented a BOW-based model for visual words in PyTorch and conducted experiments over different datasets.
- Malaria Parasite Detection from Blood Cell Images: Compared the performance of random forest classifier to a convolutional neural network to predict if a given cell image is parasite infected or not.
- Predicting Binary and Graded Lexical Entailment on Cross-Lingual word-pairs: Combined the ideas of LEAR and CLEAR to transform the input word vector space into a semantically specialised cross-lingual vector space that emphasises on lexical entailment relation.
- Fitness App to Count Reps: Built a fitness web app that incorporates pose estimation models to automatically count the number of reps as the user exercises. Developed the app using NextJS and Firebase. Jenkins, Docker and Ansible were used for CI/CD and ELK stack was used for monitoring.
- Employee Attrition Analysis: Conducted data preprocessing and feature engineering on Kaggle's HR Analytics dataset. Implemented XGBoost to predict employee attrition.
- Data Processing Toolkit: Implemented a modified version of "Minimum Degree Ordering Algorithm" in C++ which was integrated in the project to build a small-scale tabular data processing toolkit.
- Web Scraping Project: Built a Python based scraper which uses the BeautifulSoup library and extracts information from college's learning management system. Configured as a cronjob which runs every half an hour to check for new updates and notifies the user via email.

Relevant Courses

- Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning: Machine Learning, Math for Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Advanced Visual Recognition, Artificial Intelligence, Data Visualization
- Computer Science: Programming Languages, Data Structures and Algorithms, Database Systems, , Automata Theory, Software Engineering, Operating Systems, Data Modeling

Programming Skills

- Programming Languages: Python, C, C++, Java, HTML, CSS, Django, Ruby on Rails
- Libraries and Software: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, NumPy, OpenCV, Git, MySQL, LaTeX

Extra-curricular Activities

- Online Asian Machine Learning School(OA^MLS), a part of Asian Conference on Machine Learning (ACML)
 2021: Was selected to participate and present a poster on my work Firm Dynamics and Employee Performance Management in Duopoly Markets.
- Core Member, Lean In Chapter IIIT-B: Mentored girls by conducting lectures and workshops for machine learning and open source. Members have been selected in GSoC, MLH fellowship, GSSoC and various other prestigious programs.
- Curator, TEDxIIITBangalore 2019: Managed the speaker selection process and worked with speakers to curate their talks.
- Interests: Secured 91.75% in Bharatnatyam Junior Grade Exam. Core Member of the Dance Club-IIITB.